Guide to the Philo T. and Elma G. Farnsworth audio collection. 1960-1978
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 33)
  - "Alice Yarish, Examiner Interview" 8/26/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 31)
    They talk about efforts to create a plaque or memorial of sorts at the place where Phil invented the television tubes in San Francisco.
  - "Alice Yarish, Examiner Interview" 8/26/76 Side 2., 1976 (Track 31)
    Pem says that she and Phil weren't planning on getting married so soon, but because George Everson invested his money in Phil and wanted him to come to California, they got married so she could come with him.
    Before Phil received backing from George Everson, it was very difficult to find work in Salt Lake City because of the depression. He was able to find odd work doing electrical jobs but overall struggled to make much money.
    Alice reads them part of the article that suggested commemoration of Phil's invention in the form of a plaque and it was written by someone different than they had believed it to be.
    Philo III talks about his interest in creating a modular, mass producible house that will allow for much cheaper single-family dwellings.
    Pem talks about her sons' ability to play a variety of musical instruments.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 34)
  - "Cliff to 52 Russings; Russ' letters" 11/12/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 32)
    They go through some poetry, some of which is Russell's.
    They listen to a record of a man singing, which may be Russell but it's not clear from the dialogue.
    They continue to listen to him sing a few songs, sometimes the man sings alone, sometimes with others. He sings for about fifteen minutes.
    Pem reads a letter or summary of Phil's early work, with a focus on Russell and how he came to work for Phil and what he learned while working for him. It describes the actual process for television transmission as well.
  - "Cliff to 52 Russings; Russ' letters" 11/12/76 Side 2., 1976 (Track 32)
    Pem continues to read Russ' letters, which talk more about the process of the electric television as well as some of what he was working on for Phil.
    It's not clear whether she is reading only letters or another narrative that goes along about the letters as well.
    A woman tells a number of stories about Russell's family heritage. These stories lead up to the birth of Russell after talking about his parents' work and life in the United States. They sold eucalyptus oil and were not especially successful but made enough to survive. She talks about their continuing struggle to find employment.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 35)
  - "Sam Smith" 11/24/76 Side 1, Part 1., 1976 (Track 33)
    Pem talks about being approached by various institutions because of Phil's papers, and having to tell them that she was still using them.
    The man Pem is talking to was a lawyer for RCA and worked on the interference cases filed against Phil.
    He talks about the mutual respect that he and Phil had for each other and that Phil was able to avoid taking the legal action personally.
    They talk about a variety of the cases, talk about the timeline, and a couple of other things.
  - "Sam Smith" 11/24/76 Side 1, Part 2., 1976 (Track 33)
    Sam guesses that there were between twenty and thirty interference cases between Farnsworth and RCA.
    He believes that RCA won most of the interference cases, when Pem believes that RCA had not won a single case. It's hard to understand how they could have differing opinions on this, but they do.
    Philo III and Pem talk to him for a while about how to obtain patent files from the patent office that should contain more complete information than what they have at the time of the interview.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 36)
  - "Sam Smith" 11/24/76 Side 2., 1976 (Track 33)
    Mr. Smith talks about Farnsworth's system and says that it wasn't very effective in terms of quality and that he believes that was the reason it wasn't as successful as some other systems.
    Mr. Smith talks them through some of what the actual patent interference results mean, which sometimes differ from what they had understood.
    They continue to disagree on some of the points and their relevance. He believes that some of the claims were drawn too broadly and although Farnsworth had won many of the interferences, his system wouldn't work in the way that modern television needs to function.
    Most of their disagreements seem to come from a difference of opinion about the quality of Farnsworth's system compared to other systems from that same time.
  - "A.H. Brolly at his house, PTF, EGF, AHB" 6/11/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 34)
    Arch has been talking to them about a man named Albert Abramson who is writing a book about the history of television who may contact them.
    They talk about the conversation that they had with Mr. Smith but still disagree with much of what he said and clearly believe he was being disingenuous for much of their conversation.
    They talk about Zworykin touring their lab and seeing some of the things they were doing with glass tubes he was impressed by what they were able to accomplish.
    They talk about George Everson who is 92 at this point and had recently had a minor stroke.
- 1976-77, Compact disc (Disc 37)
  - "A.H. Brolly at his house, PTF, EGF, AHB" 6/11/76 Side 2., 1976 (Track 34)
    Very heavy bass sound makes it difficult to hear exactly what is said at the very beginning, this is quickly fixed.
    Arch talks about a nitrate film that caught fire in the projector room while they were working on a film at the green street lab.
    They look through some of his notes trying to figure out exactly when certain things happened, after remarking that it's been very difficult to pin down exactly when some things happened.
    They talk about Justin Tollman who is still working. They lament that it was difficult to get ahold of him as his wife was quite ill and he was awfully busy.
    They briefly talk about Tobe Rutherford, Pem explains that because his wife had fallen ill he was working again.
    Pem and Arch talk about the layout of the Green Street lab for a bit, trying to decide where rooms were in relation to each other and to the streets.
  - "Arch Brally" 6/21/77 Side 1, Part 1., 1977 (Track 35)
    Pem talks about Phil's hope that she could become interested in what he was working on and help so that they would have it in common. She says that she was always happy to have a chance to work on it with him and the other employees.
    She talks about the movie industry's interest in television and how well they were treated by people in the movie industry when they believed that television might be the next big thing.
    They talk through a number of pictures, explaining the significance as well as who is in them and where they were taken.
    They talk about some of Phil's other interests besides television, getting into his ideas of getting the virus out of the water, fusion, and other issues.
- 1977, Compact disc (Disc 38)
  - "Arch Brally" 6/21/77 Side 1, Part 2., 1977 (Track 35)
    Pem tells a short story about how Phil became interested in working on fusion.
    They talk about some of the issues that Phil faced early in his work on the television tube and Pem remarks that perhaps his best quality was that he simply believed that he could achieve what many others had thought was not possible.
  - "Arch Brally" 6/21/77 Side 1, Part 1., 1977 (Track 35)
    They talk for a little bit about the difficulties of inventing as a profession, especially the money side of things.
    Pem talks about his true passion for his ideas and how she believed that helped him to be more successful because his ability to communicate his belief in himself came through.
    They talk a little bit about George Everson's book on the subject of the invention of television but criticize it for exaggerating his role and for some of his ideas about Phil.
    They talk to her a little bit about trying to coordinate efforts to get news attention for their demonstration in September, but she wants to run the news story much sooner than that.
    The last minute of the track is basically silent.
  - "Cliff, Pem, and Philo III" 6/11/77 Side 1, Part 1., 1977 (Track 36)
    Cliff describes the process that they will be using for the September demonstration. This is highly technical and Pem and Philo III ask a number of questions to clarify.
    Cliff seems a little skeptical about their ability to actually execute this demonstration.
    They talk through some of their early designs for parts of the television tube and what worked and what didn't work as well or at all.
    They talk through some of the layout of the lab and when Cliff moved and where everything else was situated.
    Cliff tells the story about having to wash out his eyes after getting chemicals in them, trying to back up his story of where sinks and things were located in the building at that time.
- 1977, Compact disc (Disc 39)
  - "Cliff, Pem, and Philo III" 6/11/77 Side 1, Part 2., 1977 (Track 36)
    Cliff talks about his system for dispersing noble gases that he had developed in the early days of the lab.
    This is a short segment, only about seven minutes long.
  - 36. "Cliff, Pem, and Philo III" 6/11/77 Side 2., 1977 (Track 36)
    Cliff shows them a number of his patents in work related to television throughout his career.
    Cliff talks about an invention that would help with the transmission of television and how RCA had a very similar invention but were unable to actually get it to work because they missed something fundamental about how it operated.
    Cliff talks about a tube he invented that were still in heavy production at the time of the interview that were extremely profitable because of its remarkable stability that made it very popular.
  - "Harriet Stix, L.A. Times" 6/27/77 Side 1 cont., Part 1., 1977 (Track 37)
    Philo III and Pem are being interviewed for a news story.
    Pem talks about 1939, when the Farnsworth company began to manufacture equipment in Fort Wayne, Indiana.
    When Farnsworth became a subsidiary of ITT, Farnsworth began to work on other projects instead including his nuclear research. ITT moved the production of televisions to Europe at that time.
    Pem and Philo III talk for a little bit about the invention of electric television, the various claims by different people and their feelings about these claims.
    Philo and Pem talk about the expiration of some of the Farnsworth patents before they were extremely profitable because of World War II.
    The earliest investors made a reasonable return but cashed out quickly.
    The first time that RCA ever paid a royalty was to Farnsworth after it was found that the image orthicon tube infringed on Farnsworth patents and they were forced to take a license.
    Philo talks a little bit about what he is currently working on outside of the book, which is a cheaper modular house that he envisions helping to replace apartment living.
    They talk about Phil's general disinterest in television programming, but remark that he was most struck by witnessing the moon landing and that he found it especially spectacular.
    They've currently signed a contract for a made for TV movie, but a major network has yet to pick it up at the time of the interview. They question whether or not some of this is motivated by the somewhat controversial nature of the invention and early days of television.
- 1977, Compact disc (Disc 40)
  - "Harriet Stix, L.A. Times" 6/27/77 Side 1 cont., Part 2., 1977 (Track 37)
    They talk a little bit about David Sarnoff and his actions leading up to the interference case. They believe that these demonstrated pretty clearly that he was not involved in the invention of television.
    The track is about fourteen minutes long, but the audio stops after two minutes and there are approximately twelve minutes of blank tape.
  - "Harriet Stix, L.A. Times" 6/27/77 Side 2., 1977 (Track 37)
    They talk about the financial backers who financed Phil's labwork initially. Philo believes that the quality of these backers, who mostly came from banking backgrounds, indicated the quality of his father's work.
    Pem talks about Phil's early life and his interest in electronics from a young age.
    Philo recounts the story of Phil and Justin Tolman and their interactions during Phil's first year of high school in Rigby, Idaho.
    From the time Phil was 14 until he was almost 19, he worked odd jobs and things like that to help his family, which was suffering due to the Great Depression.
    Pem and Phil were married when they were 18 and 19, respectively. They had planned on waiting to be married but because Phil had to move to San Francisco to work on the television, they were married on only three days' notice.
    At the time, all of the larger companies were working on a mechanical television involving what Philo and Pem refer to as a scanning disk. This was not working well at the time, primarily because they say that the disk could not be made to spin fast enough, nor could it be machined precisely enough.
    Although it worked, it could only create a picture of 30-40 lines, leaving the picture very difficult to see. The last seventeen minutes are blank.
- 1977-78, Compact disc (Disc 41)
  - "Agnes and Laura at Larkspur" 1977 Side 1. (Track 38)
    They talk about one of their friends who often tells people about the invention of television, and her experience hearing the same story from a husband of a friend because his family had been doing reporting in North Hollywood at the time.
    They talk a little bit about how they believe Phil may have been targeted a little bit by the RFC, which was a government agency that refused to help give money to Farnsworth after World War II.
    They talk a little about RCA's offer to buy out Farnsworth and the discrepancy in what different people believed that RCA offered, some claiming that it was as high as one million dollars, which Pem disputes.
  - "Ron and Pem" 2 tapes, 3 sides Side 1, Part 1. 10/22/78, 1978 (Track 39a)
    Ron says that just before he was working for Phil, he had been a merchant marine. The amount of time that it would take for him to be promoted had doubled due to an act that had just come into effect.
    Because of this, he was less interested in sailing and thought that the job would be a good opportunity.
    They talk a little bit about the lab they were in at the time, its layout, and the fire.
    He says that he was convinced by Tobe and Phil to stay behind in San Francisco and keep working with them.
    He talks about how he became interested in machine work in the first place, during his childhood.
    He says that he remembers when Dr. Zworykin came to visit Phil at his lab and how surprised he was when Zworykin tried to claim some of Phil's inventions as his own.
- 1978, Compact disc (Disc 42)
  - "Ron and Pem" 2 tapes, 3 sides Side 1, Part 2. 10/22/78, 1978 (Track 39a)
    Ron talks about people's early misconceptions about television, and failure to understand the possibilities for it.
    Ron felt that in some of their first demonstrations Phil was too willing to allow others to try to help and it ended up reducing the quality of their earliest projections.
    Ron says that Zworykin offered Cliff a job when he visited Phil's lab, not realizing how close he was to Phil.
  - "Ron and Pem" 2 tapes, 3 sides Side 2. 10/22/78, 1978 (Track 39a)
    Ron talks about the camaraderie between those who were working in the lab in the early days.
    Pem and Ron both agree that Phil's interest in doing things that were commonly believed to be impossible or improbable was a perfect match for the close-knit dynamic of the group.
    They talk about the incredibly delicate process for creating some of the tubes for more uncommon designs.
    Pem talks about Phil's relationship with Philco and how it became strained after they would not allow him to return to Provo for the funeral of his son. She says that they were under immense pressure at the time because they were trying to establish their independence from RCA in television, which they had previously been unable to do in regards to radio.
    They both talk about their relationships with George Everson and a man named McCarter, and McCarter's feelings about those who worked in the lab, specifically Tobe who he felt was under qualified.
    They talk about everyone getting laid off at Philco and how when they tried to re-hire everyone they were all unhappy with the situation and most would not go back without Phil.
    Pem believes that eventually RCA said that Philco could only license RCA's radio patents if they also used their television patents. This was highly detrimental to Philco but they had little choice because most of their income was from radios at that time.
- 1978, Compact disc (Disc 43)
  - "Ron and Pem" 2 tapes, 3 sides. 10/22/78, 1978 (Track 39b)
    Pem says that Ski Turner and Phil had talked about trying to only license patents rather than manufacture any products, but the investors felt that there would not be enough money in it and pushed for the manufacture of television.
    They talk about what they believe was very poor management at Philco that resulted in nobody making very much money.
    Pem talks about a time where a lawsuit required Phil to stay in New York City for over a month, although it was eventually decided that pursuing the lawsuit was a waste of time.
    Pem tells a story about a neighbor who warned them about a bank run, but Phil refused to contribute to it. She says that their bank never reopened and they had only 10$ at that time, but that Phil soon received a large check in the mail and it was okay.
- Undated, Compact disc (Disc 44)
  - "Bob and Paul, #4" Side 1, Undated (Track 40)
    Disc is blank.
  - "Geo Everson" Side 2, Undated (Track 40)
- Undated, Compact disc (Disc 45)
  - "KSL, Interview with Rich Finderson – Kent and Pem", Undated (Track 41)
    This is an interview with KSL that lasts about ten minutes and covers some of the basic stuff related to their relationships with Phil and his inventions. She talks about their relationship and how she felt about him and his inventing.
  - "Frank Smith Interview, University of Utah, PTF and EQF", Undated (Track 42)
    Phil sounds very old at the time of the interview, he speaks very slowly and struggles to enunciate.
    He talks about his work in nuclear research and his expectations for his success.
    He talks about his work on a serum for hemolytic streptococcus, and how his desire came from the death of his son from the virus.
    He talks about removing the screen from television and instead creating a virtual reality environment of sorts.
    He thanks all of his original backers as well as his wife.
    Pem talks about Phil's work on fusion energy and his hopes for the impact he believes this can have on the world.
    They talk through their timeline together, where, when, and why they moved over the years and what Phil was working on.